This is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se-radio.net.
SE radio is brought to you by the ITE computer society.
and by it e software magazine online at computer.org/software.
[music]
Welcome to software engineering radio. I'm your host Javannes Proni, and today I will be discussing continuous architecture with two guests,
Murat Erder and Owen Woods.
Murat is an experienced technology leader and author, and currently CTO for financial services at Vtech in Europe.
He's an expert in software architecture and data integration, and also a frequent industry speaker. He has co-authored two books.
The first one is continuous architecture, sustainable architecture in an agile and cloud centric world, with Pier Purer.
and continuous architecture in practice, software architecture in the age of agility and devops,
with Pier Pere and Owen.
Owen is an independent consultant in the field of software architecture, green software and software engineering,
and he is the former CTO of Enava.
Owen wrote and contributed to several books,
and among them there is software system architecture, working with stakeholders using viewpoints and perspectives, with Nick Rosanski.
and continuous architecture in practice, as I said before, with Murat and Pier Pere.
I want to mention that Owen was also guest in episode 132 of the software engineer radio,
and in that case was about top 10 architectural mistakes with Owen Woods.
and this was published on the 16th of April 2009. Welcome to both.
Is there anything that I miss that you would like to add?
No, those were great introductions. Thank you.
Okay, then let's get cracking.
How do you define continuous architecture?
the core of continuous architecture, if you go to the background.
and just want to have a call out to Pierre who couldn't join us today.
but Pierre and I, this is going back 10 years,
we were thinking about we always called ourselves architects.
and we wanted to combine what is good in architecture and what is good in agile.
So the principle or the essence behind a continuous architecture is how do you make architecture relevant.
and agile.
but yeah the core of continuous architecture is the six principles,
which we'll get into more detail as we speak.
I noticed that you have things like architect products not just solutions,
or architect for build test and deploy.
So it seems that continuous architecture and compasses a bit more than the typical approaches.
and definitions of software architecture. Am I correct?
Well, I think continuous architecture focuses on getting the value delivered and empowering teams.
The reason I think, cuz I didn't write it, but I've used it many times.
The reason for the principle about build, test, and deploy is that if you don't,
[clears throat]
do those things, then the teams aren't empowered and value isn't delivered.
So, it tries to take a slightly more holistic view of what software architecture work should encompass than. just structure of a software system.
Yeah, I mean, I can add to that as well.
I mean both Pierre and I worked in consultancy and in enterprises,
and it's really about practicing architecture right.
so it's not about theoretically what makes a good architecture, what makes architecture sensible in an enterprise right.
so if you're just doing architecture maybe a very small company,
or you're building three or four people building a system,
some of these things might not be as relevant.
but it's really about practical architecture and what makes sense while you're building systems.
And another thing which we might touch upon later is the while writing the first book, which is again 10 years ago.
one question was asked to us like what's the unit of work of an architect,
and we came to the conclusion at that time.
we called it the architectural decision now,
this is before ADR's architectural decision records and other topics came about.
but that really is, architecture is about the running software in production and making it sustainable,
everything else doesn't matter.
And what really matters are the decisions you make.
that impact how that software running in production is constructed.
Okay.
And now maybe we can go in more detail into the principles.
I know that there are six of them.
Can you briefly explain those to us?
The first one is quite fundamental.
It's about thinking about a productled approach as opposed to a projectled approach.
And today this sounds entirely obvious, and I sometimes do stand in front of audiences. who look at me and go.
and you say well you got to remember these things were being thought out in 2011 1213.
I ask the audience for those who are old enough,
how many of you in 2012 were thinking about building products inside enterprises as opposed to running projects.
and very few hands go up.
It's more a reminder that actually if you take a product oriented approach.
and you think about the long-term planning.
and a product inside an organization that has a particular collection of stakeholders.
and will have a long-term life, and so needs to be managed in a sustainable way.
It drives you to thinking about all your work as building products.
Even if they're never sold outside the organization, even if there's only one copy, it's still a product.
The second principle is really fundamental to architecture in general.
It's about focusing on quality attributes. Most software architects do obsess about quality attributes.
But especially when you're introducing these ideas to people. It's actually not obvious to people.
They think architecture is about boxes and lines.
It's about structure.
The only reason for the structure is to achieve quality attributes.
Security, performance, scalability, resilience, and maintainability.
This is actually an interesting point, because often in many software products.
or projects there is a lot of focus on features.
and then the quality attributes are often an afterthought.
Exactly. and that's why it's such an important principle.
It's that the quality attributes have to be lived and breathed by the team.
You don't want someone over here called an architect who it's a problem.
And generally speaking, I'd say with all due respect to high performing scrum teams,
they can be doing a great job working with their product owner delivering features.
They find it very hard to step back and take that more holistic view, unless you remind them to.
because after all, security is not something that one team can actually achieve.
They need an environment that they plug into to achieve security.
And so that's why it's an architectural principle to focus on quality attributes,
because it's a holistic systemic characteristic.
The third principle, I suspect, because again I didn't write it, but we can ask Mur.
I suspect came direct from really the agile manifesto type thinking,
which is delay decisions as long as you can.
This is a reaction to the kind of architecture that I used to do.
Absolutely.
If you look at the software systems architecture book,
I put the graph from that showing architecture activity over time up on slides now.
so I can laugh at it, because it's my graph.
where we used to say well of course architecture.
lots and lots of decisions up front to de-risk the whole enterprise.
and then we have some decisions at the end where we realize that now we're getting towards production, we need to rethink a few things.
Of course, that's a pretty flawed approach.
Actually, as we discovered over the years, some decisions actually do need to be made very early.
And there are contexts where actually more decisions need to be made early.
But the earlier you make a decision, the less information you have,
therefore the poorer decision you probably make.
We need to make the decision as late as we can.
As the agile communities have been telling us for is it 25 years now, Jiovali?
Yeah. To make the decision as late as possible,
because that gives you the most accurate context to make the decision.
This is actually a good point, because well I worked in many projects and funnily enough.
often when people go with early decisions with grand designs of how the system should be.
and trying to overthink the evolution and everything.
what happens is that the systems have this horrible habit of evolving in a direction.
that is different from the one you forecasted.
So you end up to have to maintain a lot of stuff that you don't need.
because otherwise you cannot even compile the code plus hack into the system the things.
that will support the new direction it is going to towards.
So you may end up with a spaghetti monster that you really didn't think of at the beginning.
Exactly.
The number of people over the last 15 years who've told me I just want a futureproof architecture.
pause for a moment before breaking the bad news to them. There's no such thing.
There's just the simplest possible effective architecture for now,
and we'll maximize the options for change later by keeping it simple.
Now, before letting you proceed, I can tell you this.
that this is a real thing that happened to me in a requirement document.
a requirement that was written that the architecture has to be flexible to support future requirements.
And I explained the person at the time.
that I didn't have a crystal ball to actually be able to do that in advance.
Yeah, I'll give to a few examples about this.
For example, I mean one experience I had was people were designing the system.
and they were expecting thousands and thousands of users.
So they built a lot of complex capabilities in the system,
but it went live and it never reached that user capacity required.
So all that effort of building that was wasted.
And back to your flexibility comment, Giovania,
another thing at least maybe used happen quite a lot when rules engines were very popular.
You would say, "Oh, I need the system to be flexible.
That means I'll just write rules and I'll put a rules engine on my system. and I'll just change the rules."
Which usually didn't work as anticipated, and you just put a rules engine while not required.
Well, you could just get by with just some simple logic. So it's those type of things that.
if you're thinking you have the most future proof architecture as Owen said.
and you try to build it, you'll just waste a lot of time and effort.
and probably all architectural decisions about you balance different quality attributes.
and because you build a complex system you might overlook some other quality attributes. that you might not have thought of.
Yeah. And one final comment on this one,
presented this starchex a lot of people understand it as do not make design decisions.
and that is not the intent at all right,
we want to make design decisions as I said before,
it is the unit of work of an architect.
if you do nothing else you just make sure you know which design decisions you're making.
so it's about making them in the right context as Owen said yeah.
so to recap the first three, build products or projects,
quality attributes over functional requirements, delay decisions as long as you can.
And then the fourth one is focus on build, test, deploy, and operate.
I think this again is not about only focusing on build, test, deploy,
and operate, but it's making sure that someone is thinking about build, test, deploy, and operate.
Again, guessing a little bit reading between the lines.
Historically, software architects perhaps been quite good at debating design patterns and software structures and code line organization.
and how the unit test should run,
and actually have then left a yawning chasm between that and how code runs in operation.
I have a former colleague Edward Butler.
who I worked with quite a while in Dava who has a a great turn of phrase.
and Ed started really on the op side of the house.
and then moved to the dev side of the house.
So he for a period was very influential in DevOps as you might imagine.
and he was one of the pioneers and he had a lovely phrase.
He said on the one side you've got operations, on the other side you've got development.
and in between you have the desert of responsibility where nobody wants to tread,
because they think they're going to die.
and architecting for build test deploy operate is about building the bridge over the desert.
so that actually code can stop just being beautiful structures and can actually start delivering value in production.
Yeah to me actually this principle is something that is quite interesting,
because I think is an excellent one.
It also is something that really when you talk about architectures often with architects,
they don't really emphasize the architects for build test and deploy.
often there is the emphasis on the boxes and lines if you like yeah, I'm simplifying a bit.
but it's often on this on the structure usually on the static behavior, sometimes some sequence diagrams.
but then how are we going to test this.
or how are we going to build the pretty stuff is never discussed.
and I think historically there were reasons for that, not maybe brilliant reasons but there were practical reasons.
I grew up in a product development,
and there I mean the development team software engineers didn't deploy anything.
We had to produce a binary that came out of a build cycle.
that went to show you my age.
Something known as the gold master, meaning cuz the first CDs were always gold.
so you could tell them apart from the other CDs.
So it was stamped the gold master that went to the test team.
And actually that was sort of sane and sensible. This wasn't a cloud deployment.
This was going to have to go to a customer.
the customer was literally going to put.
that CD into a server machine and try and install the product. So the fact that you had a separate team with the skills,
the customer had checking what was coming out of the engineering build cycle.
actually made a lot of sense.
But as soon as you start operating your own software as a SAS vendor.
that suddenly doesn't make any sense anymore.
And I think a lot of big companies enterprises were set up that way too.
Do you remember they used to have no, well many still do, quiet isolated ops function.
Dev are not allowed to have any access or control over production at all.
They can fiddle in their test environments,
but there's not a very serious attempt made to sync them up.
And again, something that looks a bit like a gold master comes out of development.
and is handed to ops across the desert of responsibility.
Ops try and install it, tell you it doesn't work, and hand it back again.
Or even worse, boot it and then hope for the best in full knowledge.
that it'll probably go wrong.
and then have to deal with the fallout at half past 2 in the morning. when some other region starts using it.
and they suddenly discover they haven't got their languages loaded.
all whatever gross error has been made.
Also the test bit is actually quite interesting,
because in practice you can have something that that high level architecture two systems look identical.
from a high level point of view.
same module same things, but one is testable the other is not.
simply because you didn't think about how are you going to test this thing.
Yeah. So to me also this is quite an important point,
another one that is often not discussed even nowadays.
No, no, I totally agree.
But I think it's all about back to what we said about the principles about the team.
and a team owning the software.
So it's not about having separate teams do different things like you build it,
you own it, you operate it, right?
In an ideal world, you want the team fully accountable for the software from its conception to its.
decommission actually at some point in between.
You operate it for many many years hopefully.
And and I think that's sometimes lost on people and this distributed responsibilities of different teams.
and you create those deserts that O mentioned of no responsibility. and testing is another good thing. Right?
Testing should be done by the team.
You might have certain testing experts, but you don't need massive separate testing teams.
and thinking about how you test it,
which artifacts you test, how often you test, what do you mean by regression testing.
how you manage your test data, all those things the team should be thinking about. Yeah. And then which principles are left?
There's two.
One is architect for change, and the last one is organize your teams along the design of your. system.
Um architecting for change is it's a little bit like the testability one.
I think it's if you think about the fact the system will have to undergo possibly traumatic change. in the future.
and you think about that early without building a monstrosity,
there are things you can do to make it easier to change.
So for example, I mean your kind of expertise Javanni in domain driven design tends to produce code. that's highly modular.
with very limited dependencies and very regular structure,
making things testable early frequently allows them to be repackaged in different ways and still testable.
Building from smaller rather than huge big monolithic components.
anyone I mean I'm sure all three of us have sat in front of an IDE.
and wondered what to do with even a single class.
but a single class that's like seven.
or 800 lines of code with a small number of huge methods in it,
it's just very hard to change.
So dealing with more smaller pieces and it's bearing those in mind.
and particularly the emphasis behind this principle is as the principle says leveraging the power of small,
clearly written by Pierre.
It's a more of an American phrasing of it.
So I mean that that alludes to things like small services, not necessarily microservices,
but you know small services rather than big monoliths with lots of internal interdependencies.
or if you're going to build a monolith build it out of really well encapsulated smaller parts.
that are assembled at runtime.
And if you think about microservices and the whole debates around that,
if you combine principle four with actually principle five.
those things together will make you decide what's the best size of those components, right?
because the more, if you everything is very small,
it's very difficult to operate and monitor and manage the dependencies.
and even just understanding the message flows etc between tens of components versus a few handful is is. very different.
so I think the principles really add value when you try to apply all of them together.
definitely and then the last one is the what you said the modeled organization of the the design. of the system.
this is conway slow is it?
yes I'd say probably we've probably got less to say about this collectively the three of us than.
we have about all the others.
because it's about organizational design and generally people.
who are expert software architects don't do organizational design to be honest.
I think certainly what I've started to point to is team topologies,
because I think they've thought quite a lot about a sort of abstracted software engineering approach.
to how you design organizations which seems to work well in practice.
they've been adopted in lots of industries.
but for me actually the core of the principle is bear in mind.
if you have one structure for your teams and a different architectural structure in your software.
the who will start to overlap and merge whether you want them to or not.
because people need to get things done.
And so if there's lots and lots of discussion needed between teams, they will find ways around that.
And you'll probably find functions bleeding into the wrong modules.
You'll find strange interconnections suddenly appear between components.
You'll find components suddenly getting merged without you being told or split,
because people can't work on the other one.
So it's if you ignore the relationship between the organizational structure and the software structure, you're fairly doomed.
to the fact that the two of them are going to start merging in probably unforeseen ways.
Yeah.
to me looks like the Conway law is almost a law of nature of how organizations work.
and you mentioned team topologies, and team topologies is an approach on how to exploit this law somehow.
make sure that it works in your favor.
because it's easy to say you should carry of course is a principle here.
but modeling the organization after the design of the system as a principle does not tell you much.
about how in practice do that.
and team topologies is an approach for doing that, there may be others, but this kind of help you in achieving that.
I guess it's a starting point, and like any prescriptive abstract approach,
you're probably going to change it in some ways for your particular context. but it's a good starting point.
Yeah. Yeah.
Maybe I'll take the principle in a different way of thinking about it.
It's also about the things you care about and you can change,
and the things you care about and you can't change.
And if you find yourself that you.
and this probably works more for if you're thinking of systems of systems or more complex systems.
but if you think the perfect system you want to develop,
but it actually doesn't fit within how your organization is structured.
for example I mean in banking at the very highest level there's the front office.
and the back office like if you oversimplify it.
and if you own the back office system.
but for it to be fully successful you need your front office systems to operate differently.
you really don't have much influence over that.
So they sometimes know what you can influence,
and if you can't influence it just.
then build your architecture around that rather trying to fight unnecessary corporate battles.
Yeah.
How do you balance upfront design with architecture flexibility here, especially when dealing with a changing business needs?
Yeah, it can be quite difficult just the same as in agile software development in general.
but delay your design decisions as far as you can but not too long.
Actually finding where that point is can be quite tricky.
And I think there's two things that I use.
One is when is a decision going to be needed,
as opposed to when is the decision probably going to be irrelevant and things will have moved on.
And the second thing is how risky is the decision,
which tends to come down to how reversible is it.
Decisions that are not very reversible are ones that certainly need attention early,
and you need to be thinking about them.
Even if you don't make the final decision, you need to know what your options are.
because other decisions may cut off possible solution options for another decision.
And then when you're looking at whatever approach you're using,
but some sort of road map as to when the system's got to evolve.
For example, when you're going to go into a new region,
or when you think user numbers are going to go over a certain level.
or when a particular set of features implies big changes,
or maybe big increases in the complexity in the data layers.
that's when from some distance out you can generally see.
that architectural decisions are going to be needed before you get there.
So you then have to work back. and work out how much time do I think I'm going to need to make a good decision.
as opposed to the first thing that pops into my head.
And sometimes to expand that I mean architectural decisions what I find quite useful is to try to.
write out the architectural decisions you need to make. and not make them right.
just have that list right, so these are the decisions I need to make.
and then as Owen said then you decide when you need to make those decisions.
and as said certain decisions are very critical and non-reversible.
I think like the how you manage data in your system.
or the database technologies you use are something that's quite influential in the future of your architecture for.
example.
that is a important insignificant decision.
while some other decisions like do I use synchronous or synchronous messaging you can work around that.
and you can build components that shield you from changes and those decisions.
and in terms of evolving the architecture,
how do you incorporate feedback loops into architectural decision- making,
any feedback say from operations user experience business maybe the development teams.
how do you do this how do you implement these loops?
in the second book We wrote something called the essential activities of continuous architecture.
because the challenge to us was it's great you have these principles, but what does that really mean?
and that's why with Owen's joining us as well we wrote the second book alo. which is much more practical.
and walks you through an example of building a system and the decisions you need to make.
but if you look at the essential activities like if you do nothing else,
if you want to do architecture.
and again we're talked about your responsibilities code that runs in production.
You have to focus on quality attributes, that's kind of non-negotiable.
You have to have architectural decisions.
So we said is the core unit of work.
and then basically you have to track your technical debt, that is quite important.
We don't dive into it that much as a topic.
There's quite a lot of good books on that that are separate.
but I think understanding technical debt is important.
And we say those are the core things,
and you have to implement feedback loops to do architecture right.
You need feedback loops are depending on your organization what those loops are and with whom is.
Have you got any examples?
So there's two sources generally of information to give you a feedback loop.
One's an artifact based measurement.
One's an operation based measurement.
So artifact based measurements tend to come from the pipeline,
and they're all the things most listeners will be very familiar with.
Static analysis, dynamic analysis, complexity, security checking, code quality metrics, all those things.
but can also be things like you might be doing performance testing in one of your pipelines, that kind of thing.
And then there's the operational stuff where you tend to get some business measurements and some technology measurements.
Both of them can provide useful architectural input.
I have repeatedly found that the business measurements actually don't tell you much about the architecture.
because the business want to know things like what's the dollar value. that has flowed through the system today.
That's a very reasonable thing for them to ask,
but it doesn't tell you much about your architecture unless you understand the transaction makeup.
So this is common thing in banking.
You hear people in money markets saying, "Oh, well, you know, we do $1.4 trillion worth a year."
Okay, how many transactions?
About 40 a day.
And the equity classes look at them and go, "We do more than 40 a second."
The amount of money doesn't matter.
It costs the same to process a $1 transaction as a trillion dollar transaction to a first approximation.
So some of the business metrics can be shared, of course.
things like they may well care about peak load,
because it's giving them a business view as well as there's a technology view.
but generally for architectural feedback loops I've always found the technical measures are normally what you need to. know.
whether your architect is going in the right direction or the wrong direction.
how many security problems have you had in the last 3 months. how many failures have you had. what was your recovery time.
what's your CPU usage on okay average throughput.
it of course depends on what's important for your system.
but it's those kind of tangible measurements.
that a well operated production the system can provide you give you a lot of input. So from the business if the feedback loop from the business.
that could be interesting is anything that reflects almost directly into technical things.
like we want to serve X million customers per day for example,
which would reflect on the load of the system.
maybe indeed that can then be sort of translated into technical requirements.
and then if you measure for example raw request volume that's not actually going to give them. that metric.
but you can probably process raw request volume by working out how many unique visitors you have to.
work out if the business metric is being maintained or. Okay.
And now a question that may be a bit difficult.
I don't know. I don't we'll see.
So I'll quote you from the book.
So in continuous architecture, so in the first volume you wrote a majority of architects work effectively as.
part of software delivery teams.
and most of the time probably not even calling themselves architects.
And in the continuous architecture in practice book he wrote perhaps it is better to consider architecture to.
be a skill rather than a role.
Now what does that mean for people whose role is software architect?
providing their organization views that constructively and as long as they have great relationships with all of the.
different people who care in order to be effective.
it's absolutely fine to have a role called software architect.
I think what we're recognizing though is.
that historically that job title can be a bit of a barrier.
Not necessarily because of any one individual,
but collectively that job title can be a bit of a barrier to for example effective collaboration with. teams.
And there's also to recognize that lots of people are doing architecture work.
who even in an environment where people are called software architect there are lots of other people doing.
software architecture work who are not called software architects.
So it's trying to decouple the two really.
This was a long theme at indava.
our group head of architecture who I think both of you know Christina Cooker Bland Chris.
and she for quite a number of years before retiring from Indava about a year ago.
that she has been trying to do this within the firm.
has sort of prize the two apart.
and make architecture a set of skills.
and behaviors which it can be found right across technical job families.
and some people want to specialize in those particular things and they're called software architects.
and we solution architects and you know we have those too.
but it's not trying to corral architecture as belonging to the arch aritects.
It's very much a collective shared commons is what we're after. And there's different ways to achieve that.
One of them is to have architects working with everyone else.
But the other thing is to have no one called architect,
but there be people who've got architectural responsibilities.
Okay. So am I correct if I say.
that is a bit like when we talk about T-shaped people that have a deep expertise in something.
and a broad expertise in in other things.
So somebody could be a good developer but is also a deep expertise in architecture.
and somebody else have maybe broader expertise in architecture.
but is a better developer or better technologist in some aspects.
Yeah. Perhaps they're an expert on databases.
Yeah. is something along those lines.
So it's not that architects are not valuable anymore.
Their relationship with the teams are different from being somewhere else designing things.
Exactly.
I mean it's actually to make architecture valuable is the intent, right?
And I think in lots of traditionally the ivory tower architect gets a bad name in organizations.
because you have set up separate architecture teams.
that dip in and dip out of different product teams or project teams.
And the idea is bringing accountability back to the team, right?
because the unit of work are architectural decisions and the team makes those architectural decisions.
So anyone who contributes to that architectural decision is you could say an architect.
That doesn't mean you don't need central teams to set wider principles or wider guidelines for the organization. They need to exist.
But it's to separate this thing of like having architects on one side are the only people.
that make decisions and determine what's good or what's bad.
and everyone else as just toiling writing code. And you can take different views.
You can say the architects see them as people.
who just don't know what they're doing and make wrong all the wrong decisions.
or the people on the ground actually working to develop the software look at the architects.
and say who are these guys.
they have no idea of our software of our codes.
and they just come here with they pontificate.
So we really want to bring that together and make architecture relevant.
rather than having two separate focus areas in the organization trying to do architecture.
Yeah. Another question around the decisions.
As we mentioned before, the architectural decisions are kind of the say what architects do.
is that the main output of the work in a continuous architecture context?
How do you record them and maintain those decisions?
Because if it was waterfall, everything they said up front,
you know, I have all my decisions written, agreed, signed in blood, and that's it. I don't need to do much.
Well, written, agreed, signed, ignored, ignored. That's the the full life cycle.
But in a continuous architecture situation, especially.
when we work start from small and evolve the system and take decisions all the time.
we need to record these decisions and manage them in a bit of a different way.
It's much more dynamic, isn't it?
So how do you do that without actually being overwhelmed by the process?
It's quite difficult.
And interestingly, in the last two to three years,
I've worked with a couple of clients who were actively trying to figure out how to do this. They were very well-intentioned.
Just a sec. They met ADRs.
They sort of unleashed ADRs across their team.
Just a sec.
So ADRs we mean sorry architecture decision records.
Yeah. They picked a format.
They did some thinking about how they wanted theirs to work.
They started producing architectural decision records almost not exactly ad hoc but you know very continuously.
And they ended up with this huge heap of architecture decision records,
and it wasn't quite clear what to do with it.
And I think the lesson I learned after two.
or three times of kind of trying to help people with this is.
it's one very important to work out what you're going to do with your decision records.
And secondly, you need to put some effort into curating your decision records very early.
Otherwise, they become a sort of documentation debt, because you don't know which ones are valid.
Some of them have probably now been retired, but they're still sitting there in the overall heap.
It's very hard to find a specific decision, because there's just they're very loosely organized.
The best solution I found for that,
I didn't find a great solution but the best solution was using wikis.
because they can be hierarchical along with rich content tagging.
and so you can use I forget all the the right content term for it,
but you can effectively have a web of content linked together by the tags.
with an overall primary organizing hierarchy.
so you can go and find stuff quickly.
and find related things quickly and you link between the records.
but the thing that you have to keep persuading people to do even.
though they're busy even though they've got three jobs is.
when they hit a decision that that looks wrong,
the documentation looks wrong, flag it up and do something about it.
And secondly, on a pretty routine basis, review decisions in the overall decision base.
I'd be retiring the ones that should be retired, correct ones that are incorrect.
or at least flag things up that are inconsistent.
and particularly if they're not consistent with the principles,
because the point of the principles is to guide the decisions.
That's a really you talking about feedback loops, that's a great feedback loop.
So are we ignoring the principles when we make decisions, and so the decisions aren't great decisions?
or are we making good decisions deliberately violating the principles because the principles aren't right.
and so you need to go back and think well these principles don't reflect our priorities.
I mean there's I think two sides to like like there's the managing decisions as part of the.
process almost as implementing principle three.
is one way to look at it.
and then how you curate decisions after you've made them.
so that you have a proper knowledge base is another way to look at it right.
and and they I think they're both complimentary.
but you know talked about good ways of how you can make sure.
that your collections of decisions are already there.
so you understand why the hell the software was built in the way it does.
but also I've found using like a basic camb board of architectural decisions on a product.
and you just go through them and you have decisions as I said. that you're not going to make yet.
you have decisions you've made of course once you make a decision.
then it goes into the heap of you know how you you want to review them etc.
but that can bound board thing really really helps focus the team on just saying you know what. are the.
and that's the process of making the decisions and implementing principle three,
I think that's just as important as the post the decision is curation.
Yeah, in some projects where we work.
actually we found useful to put many decisions in the same configuration management repository of the code.
that was affected.
but then the decisions of higher level maybe in wikis.
or somewhere else basically a mixed kind of approach.
because the reason is sometimes when you even.
if you are in a continuous delivery approach sometimes you have a version in production of a system.
and you want to know what the decisions related to.
that thing not necessarily the new decisions for what you're working on at the moment.
But it's really a complicated thing.
But it definitely requires some effort from the company to actually address the problem.
Yeah.
And very dependent on the culture of the organization as well.
I mean I mean continuous architecture has principles and recommendations but it's not a you know a cookbook. Yeah.
You know in the sense that we don't tell you mix you know two teaspoons of decisions with.
one tablespoon of quality attributes.
and you know you get the perfect system.
It's just ways to think about how you do architecture.
Now moving on a bit about validation.
How do we validate an architecture in a continuous architecture context?
Well, the feedback loops are quite fundamental to it.
Um, there's nothing to stop you though doing what you might call traditional architectural evaluation on a system. that's, you know.
using a scenario-based technique like ATM or something bit lighter weight and less formal.
but you still understand the overall architecture.
Um, so you you can still do what you might call an abstract evaluation of it.
But I think the key evaluation is how well does it work, and that's what your feedback loop should be telling you.
Yeah.
The end goal is to as we said like you're accountable for the system that's running in production.
So if you really think about it.
if you know you how well the system is operating plus how.
well you can maintain it over time.
because architecture is about building a sustainable system over time, those two things validated.
but yeah I'm known as right there are lots of techniques for validating an architecture.
and there's you know and you could do architecture reviews.
or you could implement ATM you know all those things are valid.
we're not very, but this I'm not very prescriptive on that whatever works.
I I'll tell you an interesting way we validated architecture designs years ago,
and it was not my idea it was my boss's idea.
was actually we bought huge big Lego blocks like the ones that you play with.
and we had sessions where people would describe their architecture,
you know, here's the database, here's the web server, here's that component or that other component.
and they try to build it with Lego blocks on the floor,
and then people would walk around and ask questions. What if I move this?
So, if this component, you know, you could just actually physically kick a Lego block and say,
if this component goes down, what goes on?
So I mean again it's not a very formal technique but it's you know.
I think there's multiple ways but the end objective is.
if the system is working and you can maintain it over time then you're successful.
Basically in short the you know you can exploit the feedback loop.
but also you can apply some for the lack of a better wording more traditional techniques,
and they still work in the context of continuous architecture. Am I correct?
as long as you understand your system. But to be fair, techniques like ATM which are often thought of as very formal and documentationdriven,
they're not at all.
When they designed ATAM, they would typically turn up at a US Department of Defense subcontractor.
because that's was the market it was built for.
And the first thing they'd say is where's all the architecture documentation.
and this large defense subcontractor who'd spent a billion dollars would go,
"Oh, we haven't got any of that."
So the first step of ATAB is like work out how the system works.
So hopefully if you've taken a continuous approach,
you've got all your decisions, you got minimal models,
you got your principles, you actually know how your system works.
So actually assessing it shouldn't be a huge problem.
Okay?
So as long as you know what the system does, it should be fine.
Should be fine in terms instead of governance.
So making sure that the architectural decisions are implemented and implemented correctly. Yeah.
How do you approach governance from a continuous architectural perspective?
Governance, right?
We wrote about that in the first book.
you know, we had a chapter or part of a chapter on it.
And the whole idea is that, you know,
again, we're talking about the team and the team owning the architecture of their system.
and there's lots of decisions that they need to make. So when you think about governance, you want to make.
sure you enable the teams to be able to make those decisions as quickly and explicitly as possible.
But at the same time, you want certain enterprise standards.
It could be, you know, database technologies.
It could be certain techniques for logging.
or certain you know metadata you want captured at certain events etc.
So the whole idea about governance is.
that you have you make very few but significant decisions at the top of the corporation.
by the I guess the most senior architecture governance body you have.
and then depending on the size of the organization you can get to divisional level and lower levels.
but the majority of architectural decisions are still made by the team,
but they make it within the context of that.
Now for that to work you need to make sure that the communication is very effective.
You need to make sure the enterprise standards are really communicated to all the teams as effectively,
which is difficult on its own but somewhat achievable.
but what I think we lack as an industry and I don't know we even cracked this.
how you make sure that the decisions made by the teams are visible to other layers in the.
organization and to other teams right.
I think that knowledge management of architectural decisions is still a huge gap.
and eventually what happens is that something goes wrong.
Someone senior is called dragged him what's called the senior person accountable representatives.
and dragged in front of people to say well this system went down.
and you know who approved XY Z, and they don't know because they they don't have that transparency.
and after that happens then they start becoming much more strict they say.
okay now I want every architectural decision approved by me.
you know and this could impact tens of teams right.
so the I think the trick in governance is again I.
If the unit of work is the architectural decision,
you want to make that in context of bigger principles and rules set by the organization.
But you need transparency and cracking that transparency not I think is is a big challenge.
but you know it takes a lot of time.
It's a big knowledge management effort.
and you know most people who are technologists.
and want to do architecture and things like that sometimes don't want to you know focus on that.
I guess the more social and knowledge sharing aspects of developing software.
and are there any elements of the governance that can be actually automated.
you know something that maybe can end up in the build pipelines or some level of automated checks.
there's quite nice support in open source libraries like arunit for checking some quite sophisticated dependency in code.
structure implementation of patterns those kind of constraints in in code.
but that's a very microlevel architecture.
you can't really check that I don't know web sockets has been used correctly for all request handling.
you just can't check that with a simple static test.
which in that case argued is based on reflection and using annotations in the code.
to spot different types of component.
they could be useful but definitely insufficient, it's only part of the problem definitely.
Yeah, let's talk about adoption of a continuous architecture approach in a company.
where somebody says you know what we need to adopt this approach to architecture.
because we think is is a good one. Yeah, can give some benefit.
Now my first question about this is are there any specific organizational structures.
or cultures that for which continuous architecture is particularly challenging to adopt?
I think it's very difficult to adopt where there's a centralization of architecture and decision-m.
and so you you have a very entrenched team of they're probably called solution architects.
or maybe called software architects.
and they sort of work across the teams telling the teams what their decisions are.
Sometimes you can be pleasantly surprised and those teams react very positively to a more decentralized bottomup approach.
but frequently if they find it quite challenging they will advise senior technology management that chaos will ensue.
there will be no governance and the bad things will happen.
Um, and so you have to work to counter the fears because some of the fears are legitimate.
and explain how you're not trying to achieve anarchy.
You're trying to empower teams.
They're two different outcomes and how you can empower teams without it being an.
but it does require a certain change of mindset.
if there are central architecture teams who view themselves as primarily a decision-m and policing function.
So basically is introducing a company that more decentralized decision making,
and this could be scary to people that are not used to this.
It certainly can be. Yes. And that's like I mean almost going back to the first thing I said.
that was the reason we wrote the principles and the book. is to you know I guess challenge.
that structure in organizations and say there is a way of bringing good architecture and agile practices together. But you can flip it around.
I mean, I haven't experienced it, but you could say an organization that is,
let's call it, agilista or they saying they're fully agile.
and they pay no attention to architecture would be just as difficult.
because then they would say, well, why do we need architecture decisions?
We'll just go and develop.
So, I think if you're at the extreme of centralization.
or the extreme of just build it and see what happens, you know, it will be difficult.
Yeah. for a green field system.
Are there any first steps that you would recommend to a software organization.
that are wishing to move towards a continuous architecture approach?
It's about to say green field system.
Gosh, I've not seen one of those for a long time.
I think the first thing is do you understand the principles.
and what they mean for people's look behavior approach and do you believe them?
If you don't then you need to look somewhere else for how you want to achieve just design.
really.
I mean architecture I mean how how you going to do design needs to be different.
and that's not necessarily a bad thing.
but if you haven't s got some sort of philosophical congruence with the principles.
then it's going to be quite hard to make it work.
but what I always say start with the technical leadership team.
integrate architecture work into every work cycle whatever you call your work cycle sprint iteration.
and you mean think about the five activities how are you building the technical leadership across the teams.
from the very beginning. start thinking about what quality attributes are important,
and the product managers will look after the functions that will be fine.
Start thinking about making architecture decisions very intentionally.
Start thinking about the implications for technical debt. Even as you're writing the first lines of code.
and everyone's thinking it's all going to be lovely and there'll be no technical debt.
We all know you 3 weeks in you've got technical debt.
So start managing it.
And feedback loops are an awful lot easier both culturally.
and technically to put in from the very beginning than in a sort of seven-year-old system.
So it's a bit like design for testability design for feedback loops.
Yeah. Okay.
And for legacy systems instead this should be easier.
because you said you haven't seen green field systems for a while.
So for legacy what should it's some of the same steps but the constraints are very different.
So I mean step one is especially.
if you've got small number of all powerful architects build a technical leadership team around them.
and get them sharing what they're doing and delegating and people working together to really understand the architecture.
and then you're sort of reverse engineering.
It's what quality attributes do we have or what quality attributes should we have?
And how do we know what quality attributes we have?
That sort of leads you to feedback loops.
Do we know what the performance is in in production or are we just guessing?
Do we know what the security situation is?
If not, we should be putting into the pipeline and into production and so on.
You what are the big architectural decisions that we've made? What are our principles?
Let's go and like work those out.
I did that actually with a it was a company.
that does products not the sort of products that you know consumers would buy. but you know products that big companies would buy.
and for them it was a really interesting exercise.
because they got to where they'd got to and they knew that wasn't where they wanted to be. they weren't quite clear how they got there.
and so one of the things they tried to sort of reverse engineer across a sort of broad.
team of technical seniors.
was what decisions have we made along the way.
and it was really interesting in a workshop people suddenly realizing do you remember three years ago do.
you remember we decided to split the trade table.
and everyone went oh yeah why did we do that the sort of it was mental archaeology.
and there was certainly after a while you can start drawing timelines.
there was a big split here oh yeah we did.
that oh that's what then caused these problems I wonder should we rethink that now?
It's very different to doing on the green field project.
It's just you do the same things but you do them in reverse.
Seems that there is a lot of factf finding at the beginning.
Definitely though it's also I think super important not to try.
and boil the ocean as the saying goes.
It's to take it quite incrementally.
If you've got a system that's seven eight years old, it's got 150 people working on it.
It's got a product backlog and it's got some demanding product managers.
You're not going to change everything within a couple of weeks.
It's a question of taking small steps.
Like you might decide that what your key architectural decisions.
and principles are and managing something in technical debt is probably all you can do to start with.
and that might be a good first step.
It's sort of having some vision for where you want to get to.
and just like you would with the software a road map for how you think you'll get there.
And again back to like continuous architecture is a way of thinking and not a methodology.
So it's just pick whatever works.
You know I mentioned the essential activities which are the things like core things you need to do.
which is again technical that you know quality attributes architectural decisions and feedback loops.
like that's probably a good place to start.
but also one of my I mean years ago actually both Pierre and my manager.
because Pierre and I used to work together quite some time ago.
but he used to say architecture 50% of architecture is is communication right.
it's it's not about actually it's just communicating the decisions, communicating the principles.
you know, or as Owen said, communicating why certain decisions were made at a certain time.
A common problem I see with um teams that work in short iterations,
you know, say two week iterations, which is a kind of common thing nowadays.
Usually there is a problem with the time, lack of time.
Typical teams have lot of meetings and other stuff to do.
and then some time to write some code occasionally.
Well, I'm exaggerating a bit, but I think you get the point.
is is a common complaint now adding this work for around the architecture.
So architectural decisions and feedback loops and decision records and all this stuff.
How can development teams avoid being overwhelmed by this additional workload?
It's no different to any improvement.
I think you have to have the product management.
and the software development management delivery management and teams believing in the value of this.
So they have to make room for it. It's like I'm sure you've both been in the situation.
where you've been on a system and the technical debt level has risen high enough.
that progress is starting to slow dramatically.
and it's becoming quite hard to make reliable change.
That point the product managers have to one accept there is a problem,
two accept that they've probably caused it.
and three accept that in the short term they'll have to go slower before they can go faster.
Unless you can get those three points acknowledged,
it's very hard to get space to sort the technical debt problem out.
because they'll just keep driving feature requests into the teams.
and getting annoyed when they don't get their features out.
I think it's the same with this.
It's why do you want to improve your architecture work?
Presumably, that's because you think there will be good outcomes.
Therefore, it's not a huge amount of extra work, especially in a decent sized team,
but there is something that has to be incorporated into the delivery cycle.
Can it be that is actually the extra work is a lot of it is is.
actually making the decisions explicit somehow.
because sometimes with things what happens is under pressure somebody takes some decision.
but they don't really communicate this in an explicit manner.
they do stuff they change the code in some ways implement things.
and here part of the extra work is actually making sure.
that those decision are actually explicit and communicated to everybody else.
That's true. The thing that takes the time is making a good decision in the technical leadership team.
as opposed to one person just going I'm gonna make this pub sub.
because I I can't figure out how to do this using pointto-point messaging. and just go ahead and does it.
A continuous architecture approach suggests that you know the technical leadership team should know that's happening.
and there should be an ADR produced and reviewed and perhaps some discussion. That's what takes the time.
It's do you want a good decision or you know the ad hoc decision.
And in terms of let's say return on investment on the approach,
how can an organization measure the impact of using continuous architecture?
So the only way I've found to do it is ask them what problems they currently are costing. them time and money.
and establish why you at least have a credible theory for why using continuous architecture.
and maybe other techniques would help to address those problems.
and then those problems resolving or partly resolving those problems translates to time and money.
But they're hopefully things you could measure over time.
I don't think it's something that pays off in weeks. I mean, it's months and years.
Yeah. And I think there's two aspects when you think about the benefits of implementing counties architecture.
One is obviously you're, you know, you have more sustainable systems over time.
You'd have less technical debt.
Those things are explicit.
But also another way to think about it is from an organizational thing.
Going back to our central team versus decentralized, you know,
if done well, you should be reducing the organizational friction.
Yeah.
might not I mean that I think does over time impact the quality of the code anyway.
if you have more organizational fiction like.
which I would uh say that you would have lower quality code.
or you'll have it more difficult to change code quickly enough.
but regardless of that I mean part of it is about less organizational friction focus on the team. actually happier teams.
I would even go that far right.
it's about you know one reason distributed work.
and autonomous teams work so well is is one is the communication structures and organizational friction I mentioned.
but it's also the people are happier they're more productive.
so that's just I it's not something you can quantify but I think that's that's quite important.
what is the impact of AI on software architecture work?
I think it's still early days to work that out,
but I mean the two things that have been occurring to me recently.
are repository based AI agents like Lord Con.
seemingly can do a good job of keep in context.
because they've got a lot of information which they can index.
and so they should be able to have generic software architecture information expressed in text along with system.
specific software information.
perhaps expressed in graphs or structured formats as well as code.
and I think there's some potential for them to be used to sort of act as an architect's.
assistant answer questions perform analysis ideas.
for how to improve or change the system.
the Other thought I have is I don't pretend to be a professional software developer anymore.
I write quite a bit of code for myself,
but I haven't written code that goes into production systems for a few years now. but as I've used the AI assistants,
I've had quite mixed results depending on what I'm trying to do with it. and the state of the code I'm trying to work on.
And something I see reported a lot is.
that they work a lot better in an environment where the structure is relatively easy to discern.
and where a set of constraints can be written down that quickly maps to the code.
In other words, they work better when some aspects of the architecture of the system are quite good.
So it seems like architecture actually, you know,
and also clean code and TDD and, you know, more detail things have a role to play.
in making the AI software engineering tools effective.
I'd agree with that. But I mean something we're you know with the teams I've been engaged with quite a lot is.
the you know to get real value out of.
let's take GitHub copilot as an example.
is the better instruction files you write the.
and you give more guidance to AI or more context the more powerful it is.
and actually one of the people I work with basically said you know.
that person to write that instruction file is the software architect.
and that's the term they use right.
so in essence you could say that.
if you have a well ststructured system and you can articulate that in an instruction file.
you get much more value out of AI.
So actually to get value out of AI, you need, you know, I'm repeating what Owen said,
but you need a good architecture.
I think the principles still apply.
You still the way you I mean, you're still generating code.
Maybe the roles change, maybe AI does more activities.
and you know the the type of skills you have change.
but at the end of the day, AI and humans are still building systems that have an architecture.
and that still need to you know apply these principles.
Yeah, it can almost be summarized as AI will be really effective.
if we're good enough to do it without AI to start with.
sounds paradoxical but seems to be to be about right.
given that at some level neural networks work a bit like the brain to me it makes some. intuitive sense.
and I don't really pretend to deep in intuition as to how neural networks work especially at large.
scale.
but given that human beings work better in wellorganized codebase.
where conventions are clear because it reduces their cognitive load.
then you would think that perhaps a neural network also works better in that environment.
because when it's going through whatever complex pattern matching it's doing the level of noise.
that it's having to filter out in order to find patterns is much lower.
Yeah, makes sense.
Now I've got one last question.
How do you see software architecture evolving in the coming years?
Actually the future of architecture I guess is not answer the question directly.
but I'll say something about the software industry in general.
It's a very young industry, right?
And there's so little knowledge transfer between different generations.
and each generation a new technology comes along.
and people forget some of the best practices from the former generation etc.
So I think that's just a wider observation on the software industry.
It's young.
You don't actually need to be a software developer.
Yes, maybe a college degree helps, but you don't really need it.
you know, anyone who is, you know, can learn by themselves how to code.
and now with AI can probably do that either quicker can be part of the software community.
and the number of people doing development is you know increasing quite significantly.
and I think we lose things between generations.
and we try to remind ourselves that's why architecture I think goes in and out of fashion.
So honestly I I have no idea how architecture will evolve in the future.
but I think we'll still follow the same pattern.
that there will be a period that will go out of fashion again.
and there will be a period that comes back in fashion but hopefully we'll get better.
So rather than going in circles, we'll kind of go in a spiral improving over time.
But I think we'll just go through these phases of it's important,
it's not important, this is what it means, this is not what it means.
But at the end of the day,
I do believe we are building better systems and more systems than in the past.
So I think it's just incremental improvements.
Well, I suppose in a sentence, I hope the future of software architecture is continuous.
There's a relatively few teams I come across have taken this approach up yet.
when it's explained to people often people say yes that makes a lot of sense.
and there's definitely there has been perhaps an unintentional drift towards architecture work being more about technical leadership.
and less about commander control that's very constructive and positive.
I think the core of software architecture is dealing with stakeholders dealing with quality attributes dealing with decisions.
and making trade-offs between them.
and I don't think that has changed from the 1980s.
Well, I suppose software architecture emerged in the 1990s.
I don't think that's changed the 1990s.
You know, we are quite a number of years on from there. So, I don't see that changing.
I see the environment that people need to do.
that in and the technologies they need to do it with perhaps being different.
But I think that fundamental core has been unchanging. So, I don't think that's going to change.
Okay.
And you know sometimes talking about these things is kind of in my head looks like back to. the future.
because there seems to be a lot of things.
that have been you know the core of what we do has been the same for many many. years.
but somehow as Murat said we tend to forget things and then rediscover them again and again.
We do we do yeah but I like the future of architecture is continuous sounds.
and it's like an ad for that could be our slogan. Yeah.
Well we have come to the end now.
Thank you very much Mura and Owen for coming to the show. It's been a real pleasure.
This is Joan Easy for Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you for listening.
[music]
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an educational program brought to you by IE Software Magazine.
For more about the podcast, including other episodes, visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn,
Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack channel at seradio. slack.com.
You can also email us at teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SCE radio is licensed under Creative Common,
[music]
License 2.5. Thanks for listening.